Kheel, Theodore W. Records 6021
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Theodore W. Kheel Records
1935-1997
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Kheel, Theodore W.
6021
6.72 cubic feet
6.6 linear ft.
Records.
5767543
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 28, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 30, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Theodore Woodrow Kheel was said to be named for both Woodrow Wilson and his political rival Theodore Roosevelt, the result of a compromise between his politically differing parents. The settlement presaged a career in which Kheel would be tapped by mayors, governors, and presidents to settle disputes that were part of the nation's major political and social transitions from post-World War II to well into the 21st century.
Born in 1914 in Brooklyn, Ted Kheel attended public high school in the Bronx. He was awarded a Regents scholarship to Cornell University, where he attended an accelerated undergraduate law school program permitting him to earn a bachelor's and law degree in six years.
In private practice for a brief time after graduation from law school, Kheel soon was offered a position as a National Labor Relations Board attorney in Washington. Kheel's special talents as a mediator and his obvious political skills soon gave him the opportunity to move to a new war-time agency, where he was initially hired as principal mediation officer. By 1944, he had been appointed executive director of the National War Labor Board, with a staff of 2,500 who were hearing 150 disputes a week. Kheel's work at the WLB introduced him to the most important figures in the labor movement and key government officialscontacts he would use effectively in the future.
Following the end of World War II, Kheel returned to New York City and was drafted by Mayor O'Dywer to serve in the city's new Labor Relations Division, which Kheel came to head within a year. With the agreement of the mayor, Kheel was able to serve both in this position and maintain a separate, private law practice.
In 1949, Kheel was appointed to a part-time position as impartial chairman for an important segment of public transit in New York City, a position in which he would render 30,000 decisions through 1982. Also in 1949, Kheel became a partner in the New York law firm Battle, Fowler, Jaffin and Kheel. His skills in conflict resolution led an observer to remark that the firm's work began with a battle, ended by Kheel.
During his more than half a century of involvement in labor matters, Kheel was known above all else for his extraordinary ability to get feuding parties to make concessions to reach an agreement. In the important New York and national labor disputes which he would be called to mediate, Kheel's approach was to protect management rights and at the same time demand fairness to workers while also trying to protect the public interest in the issue.
Kheel's was frequently the voice of reason in settling a number of extremely difficult labor disputes of the 1960s and 1970s. Mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr., turned to Kheel to help end the 114-day newspaper strike of 1962-63. Among his most infamous cases was the strike involving Mike Quill, head of the Transport Workers Union, who publically battled Mayor John V. Lindsay in 1965-66. Kheel's efforts also included helping coordinate bargainers and mediators during the 35-day New York City teachers' strike in 1968. President Lyndon B. Johnson summoned Kheel to Washington in 1964 to help mediate 10 days of feverish negotiations that prevented a nationwide rail walkout. Kheel would ultimately serve as a mediator and advisor for virtually every New York mayor from O'Dwyer to Beame, for the Kennedy-Johnson Administration, and other presidential administrations as well.
Kheel's interests in public issues were not limited to the labor sector. The policy disputes that came to his attention as a mediator and lawyer frequently cried out for larger solutions, and Kheel was not averse to using his considerable public presence and media contacts to seek redress, especially for what he viewed as past institutional injustices or misguided government actions. Although pressed to do so on a number of occasions, Kheel refused to run for elective office, preferring the role of a labor neutral and public advocate.
Kheel was also not averse to backing his powers of persuasion with legal action: a fierce advocate for public transit, he initiated a class action lawsuit over the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey's refusal to fund mass rail transit. His most sustained crusade for the public good related to his battle to limit commuter auto traffic and control highway building in New York City in favor of increased use of public transportation. Initially attacked by Port Authority officials and some city, state, and federal politicians of both parties, many of the solutions originally proposed by Kheel, including the concept of the subsidized fare, became public policy in later years.
An early supporter of the civil rights movement, Kheel and his wife Ann become involved with the New York Urban League in the 1950s. He served as its president in 1955 and as national president for four years. He worked with President Johnson on race issues and with Martin Luther King, Jr., in a libel suit against the New York Times. Kheel's mediation skills led to important strides in hiring African Americans in the airline industry. His reputation for sensitivity to minority issues resulted in his becoming involved in efforts to add civilians to the New York City Police Review Board in 1965. Kheel was also recruited as a peacemaker in the 1968 Ocean Hill-Brownsville Teachers dispute.
Even though Kheel handled disputes for transit workers, typesetters, and longshoremen, he reveled in the finer things in life, and dabbled as a restaurateur in fine food and was a patron of the fine arts.
He once owned a stake in Le Pavillon, a leading French restaurant in Manhattan, among others. He also represented numerous artists, including Robert Rauschenberg and Christo, and was the prime mover in the realization of the long-heralded Gates Project in Central Park in 2005.
He also made millions of dollars as an entrepreneur while facilitating sustainable economic and social change. He was the lead investor in the giant Punta Cana resort, transforming 30 miles of jungle in the Dominican Republic, and helped bring about the airport that opened that country to tourists and travelers.
Finding the solution to problems such as the impact of automation on the workplace, community disputes, and protecting a sustainable environment in which mankind will flourish, to name but a few, were the focus of Kheel's interest, enthusiasm, and financial support. He was the prime mover, bringing along like-minded citizens and specialists, in the creation of organizations to find solutions to the more intractable issues facing society. The Foundation on Employee Health, Medical Care and Welfare, the Foundation on Automation and Employment (and its British counterpart), Automation House, the Institute for Mediation and Conflict Resolution, and the Earth Pledge Foundation were among the most successful of such efforts. In the same vein, in collaboration with Price, Waterhouse in 1994, Kheel formed Prevention and Early Resolution of Conflicts, Inc. (PERC), now housed at Cornell ILR as Cornell/PERC Institute.
A prolific writer, Kheel is perhaps best known for his encyclopedic work on labor law. Throughout a career that was active almost until his death at age 96 in November 2010, he was able to balance, with amazing success, advocacy of the public good and the management of a successful law and mediation practice and other business and cultural interests.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5024: Theodore W. Kheel Arbitration Awards 5776 AV: Theodore W. Kheel Interviews and Programs 6017: Theodore W. Kheel Newspaper Clipping File 6021 AV: Theodore W. Kheel Audio-Visual Materials 6021 MB: Theodore W. Kheel Memorabilia 6021 P: Theodore W. Kheel Photographs 6021/001: Theodore W. Kheel Correspondence 6021/003: Theodore W. Kheel Arbitration files 6021/004: Theodore W. Kheel Legal Files 6021/005: Theodore W. Kheel Speeches and Articles 6021/006: Theodore W. Kheel Non-Profit Organization Files 6021/007: Theodore W. Kheel Subject Files 6021/008: Theodore W. Kheel Books and Articles 6021/009: Theodore W. Kheel Newspaper Clipping File 6021/010: Theodore W. Kheel Additional Files 6021/011: Theodore W. Kheel Punta Cana Files 6021/012m: Invitation and Program for the Theodore W. Kheel Memorial Service 6059 OH: Thomas Shactman Interviews with Theodore W. Kheel 6194 OH: College of Labor and Employment Lawyers Interview with Theodore W. Kheel 6196 OH: New York City Central Labor Council Interview of Theodore W. Kheel for Central Archives 6207 OH: CLEL Video Oral History Project
5767543
- Photos of Collective Bargaining Stamp, one large, one small, small photo has Ted Kheel and President Ford (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "En L'Honneur du Maire et Madame John V. Lindsay" Dinner Menu., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  French. May 16 1968.
- Letter to Daniel Wolf of The Village Voice., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  June 24 1974
- Files in Warehouse. Material to be Copied and Sent to CM in Durham (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Hammer Galleries. FD and Eleanor Roosevelt Sale and Exhibition., 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  November 12 1951 - November 26 1957
- Genesis of PERC. On the Matters of Dispute and Negotiation., 1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Institute of Collective Bargaining and other Kheel Documents, 1959-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Newspaper Guild and Dispute. Employee Stock Ownership Plans., 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Newspaper Guild and Dispute. Reports on Employee Stock Ownership Plans, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Newspaper Guild Dispute. Employee Stock Ownership Plan Reports and Book., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Employee Stock Ownership Plan. Daily News with Unions., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Collective Bargaining and Mediation of Davis Electric and Steelworkers Local 7766., 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- The Public Domain Project Miscellaneous Documents, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Manhattan College. Honorary Degree of Doctor of Laws. Theodore Kheel., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  March 20 1968
- Collective Bargaining Commemorative US Postage Stamp. Book., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  March 13 1975
- Photograph Photocopies Made for Ann Kheel, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Frederick Douglass Awards Dinner. New York Urban League., 1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  May 3 1990
- Frederick Douglass Awards Dinner. New York Urban League., 1990 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Manuscript Photocopies Made for Ann Kheel, 1961-1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Report on Negotiations Concerning the Transportation Control Plan. Natural Resources Defense Council., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Employer Attitude and Work Integration. Prentice Hall, Inc., 1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Contains one photo.
- Impact of Automation on Employees., 1962 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Elmer Bernstein vs. Universal Pictures, Inc. Court of Appeals, Second Circuit., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  May 27 1975.
- Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Appeals Court, Eighth Circuit., 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Bound book.
- Untitled Manuscript. Pages 1-240. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  No date.
- Honors Given to Theodore Kheel. Miscellaneous., 1968-1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- New York Times Articles Concerning Kheel. Reproduction Materials., 1981-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- News Clippings and Press Releases. Miscellaneous Personal Documents. Correspondence., 1935-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Press Clippings about Kheel, Annual Collective Bargaining Forum Documents, and Miscellaneous Remarks by Kheel, 1963-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Dinner Honoring Theodore W. Kheel. National Conference of Christians and Jews., 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  June 19 1978
- Seating List for Four Freedom's Award and Theodore Kheel. New York Hilton., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  February 6 1969
- "Collective Bargaining Forum: A Series of Advanced Seminars by and For Practitioners of Collective Bargaining" (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Superintendents Work Conference Program., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  July 7 - 18 1975
- Seventeenth Annual Meeting. National Academy of Arbitration., 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  New York Hilton. January 29-31 1964
- National Academy of Arbitrators. Nineteenth Annual Meeting. Americana Hotel, San Juan, Puerto Rico., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  January 24-27 1966
- Speeches and Articles. Le Pavillon. Letter by Theodore Kheel., 1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Glossary of Terms for Book on Collective Bargaining, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Ford Foundation Letter, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  May 15 1974
- Proposal. High D Jascourt, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  August 31 1973
- Institute for Dispute Resolution. Dispute Resolution Clauses: A Drafter's Guide., 1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Videotape Study Guide. CPR Legal Program. Catherine Cronin-Harris. (Box 3, Folder 17)
- ADR Practice Tools. CPR Legal Program. (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume F., 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume N., 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Addendum to Appellant's Brief., 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Petition for Rehearing., 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Brief for Appellant., 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume A. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume G., 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume I., 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  March 1984-April 1986
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume B. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  No date
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume M., 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume D. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume J., 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume K., 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume H., 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Court of Appeals, Eight Circuit. Independent Federation of Flight Attendants vs. Trans World Airlines. Volume C. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Board of Transportation of the City of New York. Rules, Regulations, and Schedules of Working Conditions., 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  15 booklets.
- New York City Transit Authority. Budget Data, Transit Facts, Pension Plan, and Schedules of Working Conditions., 1961-1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  6 booklets.
- Metropolitan Transit Authority, Transportation Workers Union. Negotiations. "Cry the Beloved City"., 1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Newspaper Clippings. MTA-Transportation Workers Union 1980 Negotiations., 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Correspondence. MTA-Transportation Workers Union 1980 Negotiations. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Transit Industry. General Correspondence., 1955-1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- News Releases and Clippings., 1949-1964 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Transit Industry, Industry-Wide Matters., 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Transit Industry. Statement by Theodore W. Kheel. Transit Authority Order to Employees to Operate 349 Buses., 1965 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  April 14 1965
- Transit Industry. General Miscellaneous., 1959-1979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Documents Concerning Theodore Kheel and the Westway Highway., 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Transit Negotiations 1978. Transit Industry and Theodore Kheel Newspaper Clippings., 1966-1979 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- The Jurisdiction Lines for Electronic Equipment and Telephone Sub-Divisions, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  April 7 1977
- New York City Transit Authority. Platform Conductor Study Final Report and Various Studies on Standard Inspection Procedure., 1978- 1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- New York City Public Employees. Pay, Pensions, Hours and Working Conditions. Reports and Newspaper Clippings., 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Pension and Disability Documents. New York, New York., 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- New York City Transit Authority. Wage Settlement Charts and Wage Documents., 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  14 photos of charts
- New York City Transit Industry. Reports and other Documents, 1956-1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Transit Industry. Pay Board Dispute., 1961-1971 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- New York City Transit Industry. Rules, Practices and Working Conditions., 1953-1967 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Transit Industry. Negotiations of 1971. Newspaper Clippings., 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Reply to CBS Editorial. 1979 Bus Strike. Varsity, Pioneer, ATU. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  March 16 1979
- Correspondence and Memos. Bus Strike 1979. Varsity, Pioneer, ATU. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Selected Honors and Awards. Theodore W Kheel., 1948-1996 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Testimonials and Correspondence, 1938-1959 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Testimonials and Correspondence., 1960-1963 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Testimonials and Correspondence., 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Testimonials and Correspondence., 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Testimonials and Correspondence., 1970-1978 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Testimonials and Correspondence., 1982-1996 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Testimonials and Correspondence. Undated. (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Selected Photocopies of Testimonials and Correspondence., 1962-1966 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Selected Photocopies of Testimonials and Correspondence., 1975-1996 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Photocopies of Theodore Kheel Telegrams., 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Photocopied Headlines Concerning Kheel, 1965-1973 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Documents for Awards bestowed upon Kheel, 1973-1977 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Photocopies of the Earth Times Articles, 1993-1996 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- New York Daily News and the Unions. Decisions and Appeals., 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Typographical Union No. 6. Decisions and Appeals, Appeal Board, NY State Department of Labor. Unemployment Insurance., 1982- 1984 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Drafts and Copies. Daily News with Unions., 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- R Murdock Statement. Daily News with Unions., 1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  March 31 1982
- Notes. Daily News with Unions., 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Fred W Friendly's Statement. Daily News with Unions., 1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  March 18 1982
- Allbritton Communications, Inc. Proposal. Daily News with Unions., 1982 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Research. Daily News with Unions., 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous Documents Concerning the Daily News., 1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Press Releases and Newspaper Clippings. Daily News with Unions., 1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Employee Stock Ownership. Statements and Correspondence., 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Unemployment Insurance. Daily News with Unions., 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Correspondence. Daily News with Unions., 1982 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  April - March 1982
- Correspondence. Daily News with Unions., 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  September 1981 - March 1982
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Special Board. Railroad Shopcraft Dispute. Washington, DC. Volumes 2 and L., 1967 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  August 21 - 23 1967.
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Special Board. Railroad Shopcraft Dispute. Washington, DC. Volume No. 4., 1967 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  September 9 1967
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Special Board. Railroad Shopcraft Dispute. Washington, DC. Volume No. 3., 1967 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  August 29 1967
- Railroad Dispute. Newspaper Clippings., 1964-1965 (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Railroad Dispute. Handwritten Notes. (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Railroad Dispute. Miscellaneous., 1964-1966 (Box 23, Folder 6)
- The Special Board. Shop Employees' Wage, Rules and Fringe Benefits Case. Carriers' Exhibits No. 1-6. Witness: Wolfe., 1967 (Box 23, Folder 7)
- The Special Board. Shop Employees' Wage, Rules and Fringe Benefits Case. Carriers' Exhibit No. 7. Witness: Wolfe., 1967 (Box 23, Folder 8)
- The Special Board. Shop Employees' Wage, Rules and Fringe Benefits Case. Carriers' Exhibits No. 8-10. Witness: Greer., 1967 (Box 23, Folder 9)
- The Special Board. Shop Employees' Wage, Rules and Fringe Benefits Case. Carriers' Exhibits No. 11-15. Witnesses Wolfe and Greer., 1967 (Box 23, Folder 10)